A Guide to the Dana S. Creel papers FA773
Rockefeller Archive Center
Dana S. Creel papers
1955-1985
1975-1985
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Creel, Dana S
FA773
8.77 Cubic Feet 20 letter document boxes, 2 legal document boxes ands 1 half-legal document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center via the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, in accordance with the terms of access to the RBF collection.
Biographical / Historical
Beginning in 1939, Dana S. Creel served as an assistant to Arthur Packard, who was a long-time associate and financial advisor of John D. Rockefeller, Jr, and directed the philanthropic activities of Room 5600, the Rockefeller family office.
Creel served in the Army during WWII primarily in a counterintelligence unit in Asia. During his military service, he developed what became a lifelong friendship with David Rockefeller.
Creel was appointed Director of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund in 1950, and served as the Fund's first President from 1968-1975, at which time he continued his service to the RBF as a trustee.
Upon his 1950 appointment, Creel was the first professional staff at RBF reponsible for overseeing operations, distinct from the personal giving of Rockefeller family members through the Fund or otherwise through the activities of Room 5600. During his time at RBF, the Fund drastically expanded it's staff and the scope and breadth of it's programatic activites.
As an RBF trustee in 1975-1980, he led the Creel Committee in a reassessment of financial support for the Fund and its long-term committments, which helped provide financial flexibility to explore programmitic and institutional expansion and position the Fund for the next generation of philanthropic giving.
Scope and Contents
The Dana Creel papers chronicle his service to, and membership on the Board of Directors and/or Board of Trustees of, the Interchurch Center, the Martha Baird Rockefeller Fund for Music, Sleepy Hollow Restorations, and the Governing Council of the Rockefeller Archive Center.
The collection primarily documents the planning, partition, and donation of portions of the Rockefeller family Pocantico Hills, NY estate, Kykuit, as a historic site of the National Trust for Historic Preservation, and the development of the vital cooperative roles played by the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, in the operation and maintenance of the site, and Sleepy Hollow Restorations, later Historic Hudson Valley, in operating the visitation program including public tours of the house and gardens and its collections.
The Creel papers also document the early years of the Rockefeller Archive Center, 1972-1985, including the initial proposal and planning, funding, establishment of the Center as a part of Rockefeller University, and the scope and development of its associated collections, including the archival records of the founding donors the Rockefeller family, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, and Rockefeller Foundation.
Also of interest are several files documenting Rockefeller family donations, including a file of summaries of the philanthropic giving of John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. during the period 1855-1960, and later family donations toward the restoration of Lyndhurst as well as acquistion and maintenance of the Union Church of Pocantico Hills by Sleepy Hollow Restorations.
- Dana S. Creel - Day Files, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Four Centuries - Board of Directors, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Four Centuries - Cooperative Agreement (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Four Centuries - National Trust - Lease Agreement, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Four Centuries - National Trust - Owner's Agreement, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Four Centuries - National Trust - Pocantico Planning, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Four Centuries - National Trust - Pocantico Planning, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
- Four Centuries - Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Four Centuries - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 18, Box 4, Folder 19)
- Greenrock, 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Scope and Contents
  Budget and operations.
- Interchurch Center, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
- Interchurch Center - 49 Claremont, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Interchurch Center - Board of Directors Minutes (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
- Interchurch Center - Twentieth Anniversary Committee, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Interchurch Center - Insurance, 1956-1969 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Interchurch Center - Lease, Loans and Amendments, 1955-1979 (Box 5, Folder 29-30, Box 6, Folder 31-32)
- Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., 1983 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Kykuit - Coach Barn Collection, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Kykuit - The Playhouse - Calendar, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted - Rockefeller family personal - Open in 2032
- Lyndhurst - Restoration, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Martha Baird Rockefeller Fund for Music - Minutes, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Martha Baird Rockefeller Fund for Music - Board of Trustees, 1973-1984 (Box 7, Folder 38-40)
- Martha Baird Rockefeller Fund for Music - November 29, 1982 Concert, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 41)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation - Construction and Non-Construction Applications, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 42)
- National Trust - Historic Preservation Fund - Grants Management Manual, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 43)
- National Trust - Agreements, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 44-45)
- New York State Parks and Recreation Committee - Mills Mansion, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 46-48)
- Patterson Belknap - Bills, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 49)
- Pocantico Planning - William M. Dietel - Alternate Plan, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 50)
- Pocantico - The Park - Partition and Agreements with National Trust, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 51)
- Rockefeller State Park at Pocantico, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 52)
- Riverside Church, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 53)
- Rockefeller Archive Center (RAC), 1972-1985 (Box 10, Folder 54-58, Box 11, Folder 59-64)
- RAC - Governing Council, 1978-1983 (Box 12, Folder 65-66)
- RAC - Governing Council - Members, 1978-1982 (Box 12, Folder 67)
- RAC - Governing Council - Agendas, 1975-1985 (Box 12, Folder 68-70, Box 13, Folder 71-73)
- RAC - Governing Council - Minutes, 1974-1984 (Box 13, Folder 74-75, Box 14, Folder 76)
- RAC - Ad Hoc Committee Meeting, 1979 January 18 (Box 14, Folder 77)
- RAC - Conferences Held, 1979-1981 (Box 14, Folder 78)
- RAC - Family Archives Committee, 1975-1982 (Box 14, Folder 79-81, Box 15, Folder 82)
- RAC - Family Archives Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 15, Folder 83)
- JDR and JDR JR - Philanthropic Giving, 1855-1960, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 84)
- JDR JR - Cornell Resignation, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 85)
- JDR 3rd - Will and Testament, 1980 (Box 22, Folder 130)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller - Moon Property, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 86)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - National Trust - Gift Over - Kykuit, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 87-88)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Gift Over and Pledges, 1981-1983 (Box 16, Folder 89)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Kykuit Historic Park - RBF Grant, 1981-1984 (Box 16, Folder 90)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Hudson River Valley - Studies, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 91)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Hudson River Valley - Promotion and Development, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 92)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Hudson River Valley - Pocantico State Park - LSR Announcement, 1981 October (Box 16, Folder 93)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Hudson River Valley Committee, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 94)
- Hudson River Valley Studies - Aldrich Management, Inc., 1982 (Box 16, Folder 95)
- Hudson River Foundation, 1982-1984 (Box 16, Folder 96)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Board Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 97)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Fundraising, 1980-1982 (Box 17, Folder 98)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Property Committee, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 99)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations, 1980-1983 (Box 17, Folder 100-102)
- Playhouse Committee, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 103)
  Restricted - Rockefeller family personal - Open in 2033
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Kykuit, 1982-1984 (Box 18, Folder 104)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Kykuit - Planning Committee, 1982-1984 (Box 18, Folder 105-107)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Kykuit Historic Area, 1983-1984 (Box 18, Folder 108)
- Sleepy Hollow Press, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 109)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Cambridge Associates, 1982-1983 (Box 19, Folder 110-114)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Changing Plans for Kykuit Historic Area, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 115)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Kykuit Revenue Ruling, 1982 (Box 20, Folder 116)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Personnel and Consultants, 1976-1982 (Box 20, Folder 117)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Organizational Structure, 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 118)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - J.W. Harbour, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 119)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Headquarters Planning - Sasaki Associates, 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 120-121)
  Restricted - Security - Open in 2042
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Other Restorations - Old Westbury Gardens, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 122)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Other Restorations - Boscobell, Garrison, NY, 1979-1984 (Box 21, Folder 123)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Other Restorations - Lyndhurst, 1980-1982 (Box 21, Folder 124)
- Sleepy Hollow Restorations - Pamphlets and Publications (Box 21, Folder 125)
- Rockefeller University, 1983-1984 (Box 21, Folder 126)
- Union Church - Lease and Proposed Sale, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 127)
- Union Church - Day Care Center and General, 1979-1984 (Box 21, Folder 128)
- Union Church - Legal Fees, 1984-1985 (Box 21, Folder 129)
- Union Church, 1981-1982 (Box 22, Folder 131-133)
- Union Church, 1982-1984 (Box 23, Folder 134-135)